A Guide to the Anna Snowden Wildman Dyer Collection, 1849 - 1973
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Anna Snowden Wildman Dyer Collection 1849-1973
Thomas Balch Library
M 078, OMB 016, VC 0049
This collection consists of the personal papers of Anna Snowden Wildman Dyer, including her years at Bryn Mawr College (1913-1917). There are letters she wrote her parents while traveling in Egypt and Europe in the 1920s, as well as her travel diaries. The photographs in the collection document Anna's college years, her travels, and the Wildman house on Edwards Ferry Road. The collection also includes material from the estates of several family members.
Elizabeth Seccombe Smith, Pennsylvania
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Elizabeth Seccombe Smith, Pennsylvania.
Alternative Form Available
None.
Accruals
2000.0002; 2006.0145; 2007.0127
Biographical Information
Anne Snowden Wildman Dyer, known to her family and friends as Anna, was born on 7 July 1895 in Leesburg, Virginia, the daughter of Christiana (generally called Christine or Chris) Rogers Wildman (1872-1943) and Robert Bentley Wildman (1849-1934). Both of her parents came from established and well-connected families in Loudoun County. Anna graduated from Bryn Mawr College in Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania in 1917 and worked for the War Trade Board in Washington, D.C. In 1921 she obtained a teaching certificate and began teaching in the Loudoun County schools.
In early 1921 Anna made an extended trip to Egypt and Europe in the company of a college friend and her friend's mother. She made three more long trips to Europe in 1923, 1925, and in 1928. Her letters to her parents recount the first trip in considerable detail, and she kept diaries of all of the trips as well as taking extensive photographs.
In 1932 she married Archibald Murray Dyer (1907-1970), an English journalist and author. Dyer was born in Tokyo, Japan and came to the United States in 1929. He became a U.S. citizen in 1937. The couple lived first in New York, where he worked as a writer for CBS and NBC. He published one novel about Japan, The Bridge of Heaven, and wrote an unpublished novel titled The Lonely Command. They later moved to Leesburg to the home where Anna grew up on Edwards Ferry Road. They shared the house with Anna's sister, Christine Clagett Wildman (1898-1958). Murray Dyer died June 4, 1970 and Anna Dyer died on August 25, 1973.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the personal papers of Anna Snowden Wildman Dyer, including her years at Bryn Mawr College (1913-1917). There are letters she wrote her parents while traveling in Egypt and Europe in the 1920s, as well as her travel diaries. The photographs in the collection document Anna's college years, her travels, and the Wildman house on Edwards Ferry Road. A set of photographs document the military service of Lawrence Layton (1894-1918), a pilot in the U. S. Army Service during World War I. Layton died in combat over France. Also included are a published novel, an unpublished manuscript, and a diary detailing the last days of World War II in Australia, all written by Murray Dyer. In addition, the collection includes material from Anna's sister, Christine Clagett Wilman. Christine serves as the administrator of the estates of several family members, including her parents; her uncle John B. Wildman (1855-1945); and her aunt, Katherine Longden Wildman (1861-1943).
Arrangement
Box:folder
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"A. Murray Dyer," The Washington Post, June 5, 1970.
Anna Snowden Wildman Dyer Collection, 1849-1973 (M 078), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Frain, Elizabeth. Union Cemetery, Leesburg, Loudoun County, Virginia: Plats A and B 1784-1995. Lovettsville, VA: Willow Bend Books, 1995.
Loudoun County Cemetery Database, http://www.leesburgva.gov/index.aspx?page=940 (accessed 17 October 2013).
"Murray Dyer, 63, Newsman and Novelist," The Washington Post, June 6, 1970.
Other Finding Aid
PastPerfect Catalogue Records
Related Material
Nancy Graham Rogers Collection (M 058), Elizabeth Welbourne Seccombe (M 089)
Contents List
    - Baptismal certificate, n.d.
    - Bryn Mawr: academic paper on Marlowe, n.d.
    - Bryn Mawr: academic papers, 1914
    - Bryn Mawr: academic paper, Troilus and Cressida, 1915
    - Bryn Mawr: academic paper, Free Trade, 1916
    - Bryn Mawr: academic paper, The Fabian Society, 1917
    - Bryn Mawr: correspondence, October 1915-November 1915
    - Bryn Mawr: correspondence, November 1915-January 1916
    - Bryn Mawr: correspondence, January 1916-February 1916
    - Bryn Mawr: correspondence, March 1916-May 1916
    - Bryn Mawr: Examinations, 1899-1910
    - Bryn Mawr: Examinations, 1913-1915
    - Bryn Mawr: Examinations, 1916-1917
    - Bryn Mawr: Literature notebook, ca. 1913-1917
    - Bryn Mawr: Literature notebook inserts, ca. 1913-1917
    - Bryn Mawr: Record of studies, 1917
    - Calling cards: Anna Dyer and Christine Rogers (her mother)
    - Genealogical information: Bentley, Hamilton, Rogers
    - Travel: correspondence, January 1921
    - Travel: correspondence, 2 February 1921-21 February 1921
    - Travel: correspondence, 25 February 1921-29 March 1921
    - Travel: correspondence, 1 April 1921-11 May 1921
    - Travel: Esperanto key
    - Travel: diaries, 1921; 1923-1924
    - Travel: diary, 1928
    - Travel: passports, 1921, 1923, 1928, 1930
    - Travel: publications about trip to Egypt, 1921
    - Murray Dyer: diary documenting end of World War II in Australia, 1945
    - Murray Dyer: joke hunting license, 1954
    - Murray Dyer: letters of condolence, 1970
    - Murray Dyer: letters of condolence, 1970
    - Murray Dyer: obituaries, 1970
    - Murray Dyer: records of flowers for funeral, 1970
    - Christine Claggett Wildman (Anna's sister): annuity
    - Christine Claggett Wildman: estate of John B. Wildman, 1946
    - Christine Claggett Wildman: estate of Katherine L. Wildman, 1939-1944
    - Christine Claggett Wildman: estate of Katherine L. Wildman, 1945
    - Christine Claggett Wildman: Katherine L. Wildman, farm correspondence, 1942-1944
    - Christine Claggett Wildman: passports and smallpox vaccine, 1929, 1936, 1951
    - Christine Rogers Wildman (Anna's mother): estate, 1943
    - Christine Rogers Wildman: newspaper clippings
    - Robert Bentley Wildman (Anna's father): estate, 1935
    - Bag for ham from Rokeby, n.d.
    - Lawrence Layton, cemetery record: Belleau Wood, Chateau Thierry, World War I
    - Letter of commendation from War Trade Board, 1918
    - Reviews of books (author unknown), 1952-1955
    - Teaching certificate and contract, 1921
    - Wedding announcement, Anna Snowden Wildman and Archibald Murray Dyer, 1935
    - The Lonely Command: pages 1-3
    - The Lonely Command: pages 44-75
    - The Lonely Command: pages 76-105
    - The Lonely Command: pages 106-145
    - The Lonely Command: pages 146-177
    - The Lonely Command: pages 178-205
    - The Lonely Command: pages 206-257
    - The Lonely Command: pages 258-300
    - The Lonely Command: pages 301-344
    - The Lonely Command: pages 345-388
    - The Lonely Command: pages 389-446
    - The Lonely Command: pages 447-505
    - Dust cover of The Bridge of Heaven by Murray Dyer
    - The Bridge of Heaven by Murray Dyer, first edition, inscribed "to Margaret and Armistead with my love, Murray." Harper and Brothers, New York, 1952
    - Reviews of The Bridge of Heaven
    - 3 x 5 inch recipe cards
    - Wildman Family Bible
  - Class Photograph, Bryn Mawr, (see VC 0049) 1917
  - Class Photograph, Leesburg High School, (see VC 0049) 1931
  - Family Bible records (see end of M 078 for volume
  - Diplomas
    Thurston-Gleim Preparatory School, 1913
    Bryn Mawr College, 1917
  - Survey, Edwards Ferry property, 1975
    - Robert Bentley Wildman and Christiana (Christine) Rogers Wildman, parents of Anna Wildman Dyer, vc_0049_0001 to vc_0049_0006
    - Christiana (Christine) Rogers Wildman, Anna's mother, vc_0049_0009 to vc_0049_0010
    - Robert B. Wildman, Jr. (1894-1895), Anna's brother, vc_0049_0011 to vc_0049_0014
    - Anna as a child, vc_0049_0015 to vc_0049_0025
    - Anna as a child, vc_0049_0026 to vc_0049_0036
    - Wildman house on Edwards Ferry Road in Leesburg, VA, vc_0049_0037 to vc_0049_0041
    - Group photograph with Anna, vc_0049_0042 to vc_0049_0073
    - Anna and friends, vc_0049_0074 to vc_0049_0096
    - Anna and friends at Bryn Mawr College, vc_0049_0097 to vc_0049_0129
    - Lawrence Layton, vc_0049_0130 to vc_0049_0148
    - Lawrence Layton, World War I flight school in France, vc_0049_0149 to vc_0049_0168
    - Lawrence Layton's grave in France, vc_0049_0169_0176
    - Egypt, 1921, vc_0049_0177 to vc_0049_0183
    - England, 1925, vc_0049_0184 to vc_0049_0209
    - Murray Dyer, vc_0049_0210 to vc_0049_0215
    - Christine Claggett Wildman, Anna's sister, vc_0049_0216 to vc_0049_0227
    - France and Italy, 1928, vc_0049_0228 to vc_0049_0262
    - Murray and Anna Dyer at home, in Wildman house in Leesburg, vc_0049_0263 to vc_0049_0268
    - Party at Locust Hill, home of Mr. and Mrs. Burdette Wright, 1940s, vc_0049_0269 to vc_0049_0273
    - Athletics, vc_0049_0274 to vc_0049_0282
    - Automobiles, vc_0049_0283 to vc_0049_0289
    - Boats and boating, vc_0049_0290 to vc_0049_0296
    - Historic houses, vc_0049_0297 to vc_0049_0302
    - Horses, Landscapes, and Farm Equipment, vc_0049_0303 to vc_0049_0338
    - Posing Group Photographs, vc_0049_0339 to vc_0049_0362
    - Posing Individual Photographs, vc_0049_0363 to vc_0049_0389
    - Photograph album, trip to Egypt and Europe, 1921